Guide to the Carl Feiss papers, [ca.1928]-1991
Feiss, Carl papers, [ca.1928]-1991
- Series II. Professional Papers
  - Publications and Speeches
    - San Juan, Puerto Rico: "A Report on the Renewal Possibilities of the Historic Triangle of the City of San Juan for the Municipal Housing Authority of the Capital of Puerto Rico," May 1955. (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Syracuse, New York: "Interim Report on Background Studies: University Hill General Neighborhood Renewal Plan," August 2, 1965. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Washington, D.C.: "A Landmark Preservation Program for the District of Columbia," October 1962. (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Washington, D.C.: "A Program for Landmarks Conservation in the District of Columbia," February 1963. (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Washington, D.C.: "Reconnaissance Study of the Downtown Business Area," December 1958. (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Washington, D.C.: "The Washington Skyline," May 1964. (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - "The President's Advisory Committee on Government Housing Policies and Programs: A Report to the President of the United States," December 1953 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - "The Tellico Community Program Memorandum," January 17, 1968. (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - "Tuscon Regional Plan, Inc.: A Forward Look: A Report to the Board of Directors," July 1959. (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - "The Urban Resource: An Investigation Into Sources of Knowledge of the Role of Cities and Metropolitan Areas in the Economic and Social Structure of the United States," March 9, 1956. (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - "Proposed New Communities Program," April 16, 1969. (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - "A Focus for National Urban Development Transportation Policies in Metropolitan Centers," July 31, 1961. (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - [empty] (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - University of Florida: 27th Annual Southern Conference on Gerontology, March 28-31, 1978. Correspondence, programs, participant list for the conference. (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Forest Landscape Design and Management Workshop, Florida Forest Service, June 15-16, 1978. Correspondence, program for the conference. "Glossary of Architectural and Construction Terms.", 1976 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - University of Florida: 4th Annual University of Florida Conference on Florida Growth Policy: "Planning for Florida's Growth: Balancing the Immediate Needs of Our Economy and the Timeless Necessity of Our Environment," January 30-31, 1976. (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - University of Florida: Selected Conference Papers of the 4th Annual University of Florida Conference on Florida Growth Policy. Ed. Richard H. Schneider, May 1976. (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - University of Florida: 3rd Annual Conference on Florida Growth Policy. Florida's Growth: Where Are We and Where Are We Going: Prepared Conference Papers, January 10-11, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - "Urban Migration in America: A Study Proposal," February 1975. (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Manpower allocation chart. Project administration chart. Budget, March 31, 1975-March 30, 1976. Vita of Carl Feiss. Vita of Madyln Kafolis. Vita of Dr. James F. Burns. Vita of Wayne Rarcher. Professional correspondence. "Toward a Policy Planner's View of the Urban Settlement System," by Peter A. Morrison. January 1975. "Recent Research Insights Into Local Migration Flows," by Peter A. Morrison and Daniel A Relles, February 1975. (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - "Work Paper 5: Transfer of Development Rights: A New Concept in Land Use Management," March 20, 1974. "Work Paper 6: Experiences of Florida in Planning for Land Use," April 30, 1974. "Work Paper 7: Environment and Florida Voters: Their Concerns on Growth; Energy; Pollution; Land Use; In-Migration Taxes; Politics and the Future of the State," June 1974. "Work Paper 8: Takings, Due Process and the Police Powers: An Analysis of Judicial Approaches to Land Use Regulations in Florida," January 15, 1975. "Working Paper 9: Compensable Regulations: Policy Issues and Options," February 12, 1975., 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - "Work Paper 10: Standards for Urban Development in the United States: Development Standards, Systems and Regulations Used for Their Implementation in Urbanizing America," May 1, 1968., 1975 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - "Technical Assistance to Bradford County in Developing a Land Use Plan: A Basic Research Document," June 1974. (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Professional correspondence. Florida Environmental and Urban Issues, April 1977. University of Florida Urban and Regional Planning Program for the academic year 1977-1978., 1973-1978 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Conferences and Education Interests
    - University of Florida: Course Outline for AE 581: Survey of Architectural Preservation, Restoration, and Reconstruction. Professors Reeves and Feiss., 1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Urbanization in the South: A Critique and Analysis. Eds. David Colburn, George Pozzetta, Richard Scher. Feiss' "Urbanization in the South" is included in this collection., 1973 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re: Feiss' resignation as director of Urban and Regional Development Center, 1975. Draft of handbook on Urban Studies at the University of Florida, 1972-1973. Handbooks on Urban Studies at the University of Florida, 1973-1974, 1974-1975., 1972-1975 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Memoranda, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Professional correspondence with Lewis Dismukes, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Copy of letter from Herschel Shepard to Gerry Wilson re: "'Historic Inventory' ? Consolidated ?Jacksonville'" June 8, 1973. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence between Eric Hill Associates and Department of Architecture, University of Florida re: Jacksonville Florida's neighborhood development program, Architecture/Historical Survey. Brochure "Jacksonville's Neighborhood Development Program.", 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - "Historic American Building Survey: 1972 Summer Field Projects." (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Papers, correspondence re: "Florida Bicentennial Commission's Symposium on Eighteenth Century Florida and its Borderlands." Program of symposium., 1972 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Reports 1 and 2 on Interface-4, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Materials on planning education from Gerald R. Mylroie, Director of Manpower and Education, American Institute of Planners., 1971 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Letters of recommendation from Norman H. Thomson, Jr., Director of Tampa Bay Regional Planning Council; Nathaniel S. Keith, Urban Renewal Consultant; James Biddle, President, National Trust for Historic Preservation. Letter from Elizabeth M. Eddy, Director of Urban Studies Bureau offering Feiss a position as Professor of Architecture and Urban Studies, March 16, 1971. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Feiss' itineraries for visits to University of Florida., 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Master of Engineering and Master of Public Administration at New York University., 1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Memorandum from The BAC Committee on Accreditation to Friends of the Boston Architectural Center re: a report from the National Architectural Accrediting Board, October 14, 1971. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with and re: Dr. John R. Silber, President, Boston University. Feiss' notes from meeting with Silber, July 6, 1971. (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "Boston University Report of the Treasurer," June 30, 1970. "Abridged Transcript of Long Range Planning Progress Report," by Calvin Lee, acting President of B.U., October 23, 1970. Executed Application form HUD 4501 for College Housing Assistance, June 10, 1971., 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - "Making New Leadership Effective: Boston University," by McKinsey and Co., Inc., June 22, 1971. "Boston University: Charles River Campus, Future Development Study," by Harvard Graduate School design team of Buff, Lopez, Nerikar, Polydorides, Ross, Simmons, Spring 1971. "Housing Questionnaire Analysis," by Susan R. Bruce, May 13, 1971. Article on Silber's appointment., 1965-1971 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Northwood Institute: catalogs, correspondence., 1969-1971 (Box 11, Folder 19-20)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art: catalogs, newsletters, magazine, photo, correspondence and summary report of Cranbrook Academy of Art Goals Conference, March 7-9, 1969., 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - "Creativity in a Confused World," commencement address to the Cranbrook Academy of Art, Birmingham, Michigan, June 5, 1969. Earlier drafts of this address. (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art: address by Eliel Saarinen about Cranbrook, department of architecture and design brochure, newspaper clipping, correspondence, press release. Cranbrook Financial Reports, 1966-1968. Prints of plans for "Concours pour l'Amenagement de la Rive Gauche de l'Escaut.", 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art Newsletter, Spring 1967. (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - George Washington University: correspondence re:, notes and appendix to meeting of the Advisory Committee on Urban and Regional Planning, June 14, 1967. Brochure for G.W.U. Graduate Study in Urban and Regional Planning. Draft of brochure. Correspondence re: Professor Julian Kulski's resignation. (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - University of Denver: Political Science 205.5: Government Planning. Notes on students grades, attendance sheet, correspondence with university registrar re: errors in transcripts., 1943 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - University of Denver School of Architecture and Planning brochure., 1950? (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Letter from Albert C. Jacobs, Chancellor of University of Denver re: Feiss' departure for Washington, D.C., December 31, 1949. (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - First Denver Congress on Air Age Education, held at Denver, Colorado, July 23-28, 1945. (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Columbia University Housing Courses, Fall Semester 1944-1945. (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Bulletin of Washington University: The School of Architecture, June 15, 1947. Education News-letter 3, June 1948. Education News-letter 4, February 1949., 1947-1949 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - "Citizen Support for Los Angeles Development," by Charles W. Eliot, April 1945. "Local Planning Institute Syllabus-Notebook," October 1943. "Planning Education for Architects and the National Defense," address to the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture, Chicago, Il., May 11, 1941. "Education for Planners," by Hugh S. Morrison, June 1942., 1941-1945 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Memorandum to Feiss inviting him to present the proposed School of Architecture at the University of Denver, May 18, 1926. Memorandum on Planning Education: A survey of the Curricula in 23 Colleges and Universities from Walter Blucher, May 1942. Memorandum re: Chancellor's meeting with University of Denver Trustees about proposed architectural school from Len Currie, June 12, 1946. "Proposed Planning and Architectural Curriculum for University of Denver." Handout "The Education of the Architect" from the University of Toronto. "Architecture, the Expression of the Materials and Methods of Our Times," by Le Corbusier., 1926-1942 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence with Leopold Arnaud, Dean of the School of Architecture, Columbia University., 1944 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence with Leopold Arnaud, Dean of the School of Architecture, Columbia University re: Feiss' resignation, 1943. "Property Development Costs," by Ralph Eberlin, October 27, 1936., 1936-1943 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Letter of appointment as Assistant Professor of Architecture in Columbia University, April 5, 1943. (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence with Columbia University. Notes on Columbia University Class "Discussions on Urbanism," revised February 2, 1943., 1942-1943 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Letter of notification Feiss' leave of absence without salary for the academic year 1943-1944. Program, notes, and correspondence re: "Program of War Housing Management Conference-Course," June 26-30, 1942., 1942-1944 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - "Community at Work: A Lesson for Others," by Gertrude Samuels, The New York Times Magazine, August 6, 1950. Columbia University Bulletin of Information, Announcement of the School of Architecture, 1941-1942. Papers, correspondence with Columbia University re: post-war planning., 1941-1950 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence re: Feiss' leave of absence. Pgs. 771-772 of The New Republic, June 11, 1942. Three copies of The Independent Journal of Columbia University, November 13, 1946., 1936-1942 (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Preliminary outlines of proposed lectures for "An Introduction to City and Regional Planning." Notes "for use in preparing lecture outline in 145-146 for 1940-1941, June 4, 1940. Poster for Western Reserve University's lecture series "City Planning and Better Housing." "Menander Speaks on City Planning in India." Correspondence between Dean Arnaud, Frank Mechau, and Harry Carnohan re: shaving to avoid confusion between Mechau and Carnohan., 1932-1941 (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Professional correspondence with J.R. Greenberg, Chair of Speakers Bureau FAECT Committee on Housing, with Frances Schwab, Administrator, Laboratory School of Industrial Design. Pamphlets from the Design Laboratory., 1939-1940 (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Papers from National Conference on Planning: Committee on Planning Education: "Training of Professional Students in Universities and Colleges." "Adult Education." "Status and Progress of Planning Instruction in Institutions of Higher Education in the United States.", 1938 (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Professional correspondence with F. Schwab of Laboratory School of Industrial Design, with Federation Technical School., 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 44)
    - Paper by William C. More on planning of tourist regions., 1938 (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence with Massachusetts Institute of Technology., 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Sir Raymond Unwin's lectures at Columbia University School of Architecture, Planning and Housing Division., 1937-1939 (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Environmental Design Conference on City Centers in Transition, Rougement, North Carolina, June 6-8, 1976. Correspondence re:, programs of, clippings about, and notes for an address to the conference. (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Environmental Design Conference on City Centers in Transition, Rougement, North Carolina, June 6-8, 1976. Folder from conference, correspondence, itinerary, notes. (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - University College, University of Kentucky. Correspondence, clippings., 1973 (Box 11, Folder 50)
    - To Secure A Lasting Tourism Seminar, San Juan, Puerto Rico, January 6-9, 1972. Correspondence, program, papers: "The Historic, Environmental and Scenic Heritage of the Caribbean," "Recommendations to the Caribbean Travel Association." (Box 11, Folder 51)
    - New Towns Conference, Nashville, Tennessee, March 26-28, 1971: correspondence, programs. (Box 11, Folder 52)
    - Indiana University: correspondence; notes from trip to Indianapolis, March 5, 1971; clippings re: renewal and Indiana Preservation Act (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - First Michigan Historic Preservation Conference, Grand Rapids, Michigan, May 8-9, 1970: correspondence. (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Boston National Conference on Architectural Preservation, Boston, Massachusetts, April 23-26, 1970: correspondence., 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - 31st National Conference on Religious Architecture: correspondence, clippings, program. Regional Preservation Workshop, Chicago, Illinois, May 4-5, 1970: program. Announcement for International Congress on the Communication of Culture Through Architecture, Arts, and Mass Media, Brussels, September 7-12, 1970. (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - New Towns and Cities for Pennsylvania Seminar, Camp Hill, Pennsylvania, April 18, 1970: correspondence, program, policy statement, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - [empty] (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Transportation for New Towns and Communities Workshop, Washington, D.C., December 15-16, 1969: correspondence., 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers, Winston-Salem Student Chapter Advisory Conference, Winston-Salem, North Carolina, November 21, 1969: correspondence, program. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - First Annual Conference on Historic Preservation, Bloomington, Indiana, September 18-20, 1969: Proceedings, correspondence. Second Annual Conference on Historic Preservation, Bloomington, Indiana, October 8-10, 1970: correspondence, programs., 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - UNESCO (United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization) Meeting of Experts for the Establishment of an International System for the Protection of Monuments and Sites of Universal Interest: Unesco House, Paris, France, July 21-215, 1969: correspondence, papers, final reports, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Recommendation on International Principles applicable to Archeaological Excavations, adopted by the General Conference [UNESCO] at its Ninth Session, New Delhi, India, December 5, 1956." International Campaign for Monuments: UNESCO, 1964. Correspondence between Chairman of the U.S. National Committee of ICOMOS, Dr.. J.O. Brew and Professor R.M. Lemaire., 1956-1971 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - National Committee on Urban Growth Policy, San Juan, Puerto Rico, February 21-23, 1969: correspondence (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Regional Planning Seminar, Nashville Tennessee, November 26, 1968: correspondence, clippings, programs. "Nashville 1969: An Investment in the Future.", 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Ditchley Foundation: clippings, newsletter, publications, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - [empty] (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Ditchley Foundation: correspondence, pamphlet on the foundation., 1968 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - First Edward T.T. Williams Convocation, Farleigh Dickinson University, Hackensack, New Jersey, March 5-7, 1968: correspondence, notes, papers, program. Brochure for the University. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Smithsonian Symposium 1967: The Quality of Man's Environment, Washington, D.C., February 16-18, 1967: "Information for symposium participants," invitation to symposium, calendar of events at the Smithsonian, program with notes written on it, brochure on the symposium, symposium poster, paper, "informal listing of acceptances as of 2/13/67." Pamphlets to the National Gallery of Art, Museum of History and Technology, Belmont. Map of Washington, D.C. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Virginia Bearing Wall Conference, Charlottesville, Virginia, March 31-April 1, 1966: correspondence, proceedings, program, roster, tourist pamph19let. (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Symposium on Environmental Quality, Washington, D.C., March 8-9, 1966: correspondence, program (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - White House Conference on International Cooperation, Washington, D.C., November 1965: correspondence, call for papers. (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - White House Conference on Natural Beauty, Washington, D.C., May 24-25, 1965: correspondence, invitation, papers, draft of Feiss' address, clippings. (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - White House Conference on Natural Beauty, Washington, D.C., May 24-25, 1965: correspondence, memoranda, room assignments, press releases. "Urban Waters," address to conference, May 24, 1965. (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - The Kennedy Conference on New Jobs and New Growth, Charleston, West Virginia, September 19, 1960: correspondence, notes, draft of address to conference [?]. (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - El CINVA (El Centro Interamericano de Vivienda): correspondence, calendar of Feiss' visit, clippings about his visit., 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Professional correspondence., 1936-1942 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Alfred Bettman Foundation Symposium, Cincinnati, Ohio, February 24-25, 1967: correspondence, program, notes, "starter questions for discussion participants." Invitation to Feiss to join Alfred Bettman Foundation's board of trustees. (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - American Institute of Architects: correspondence., 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Professional correspondence., 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - "Historic Preservation Districts Zoning Ordinances of Marion County, Indiana," December 17, 1968. "Annual Report of the Historic Building Committee to the Board of Directors, The American Institute of Architects," by F.B. Reeves and I. Stein, October 26, 1968. "Model Cities and the Urban Crisis?An AIA Chapter Action Program," February 12, 1968. Programs from the AIA Convention 1968. Correspondence re: selection of Fellows for the Washington Metropolitan Chapter, AIA., 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Washington Metropolitan Chapter, AIA: convention programs; notes on Design in Federal Programs Workshop, September 1, 1967; chapter meeting notes; press releases; "Statement of the American Institute of Architects on S.1245, D.C. Freeway Airspace Utilization Act and S.1246 D.C. Public Space Utilization Act before the Senate Committee on District of Columbia Subcommittee on Business and Commerce," July 25, 1967. (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Professional correspondence., 1967 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Professional correspondence. "Our Sick Cities," by Ben Shahn, article in Look, September 21, 1965. (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Professional correspondence., 1964 (Box 12, Folder 30-31)
    - Professional correspondence with Union Internationale des Architects., 1964 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Professional correspondence with members of Washington Metropolitan Chapter, AIA., 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Mailings from Washington Metropolitan Chapter, AIA., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Mailings from Colorado Chapter, AIA., 1943-1944 (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Minutes of AIA Board of Directors meeting, December 2-5, 1970. "Statement by the American Institute of Architects Concerning Post-Interstate Highway System Before House Committee on Public Works," May 6, 1970. "Exchange of Information: Summaries of minutes for Committees which have met since last reporting date, October 31, 1969, and have not been previously submitted.", 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Letters of appointment to office in the American Institute of Architects (AIA)., 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - "Structure and Services Directory: Board of Directors, Commissions and Committees, Associated Organizations, Headquarters Staff, Officers and Executives of Chapter and State Organizations," AIA 1969. (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - Professional correspondence re: the Commission on Architectural Design., 1965 (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Professional correspondence., 1964 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Organizations
    - Commission on Architectural Design, AIA: correspondence., 1964 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Urban Planning and Design Committee, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas., 1970-1972 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
    - Letter from Feiss (Chairman, Subcommittee on Urban Growth Legislation) to Urban Planning and Design Committee, August 11, 1970. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Urban Planning and Design Committee, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, memoranda, reports., 1970 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Publications on New Towns: "Planned Unit Development and New Towns," by William L. Slayton; clippings from Home Builder News, December 8, 1969; Philadelphia Inquirer, November 23, 1969; Daily Pac. Builder, November 20, 1969., 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Design-in-Urbanization Workshops, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, memoranda, notes, bibliography., 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - New Towns Task Force, AIA: correspondence, memoranda, draft budget., 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)